<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on David Lilien</title>
    <link>https://dlilien.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on David Lilien</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2022 David Lilien</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dlilien.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Finally made it to Greenland!</title>
      <link>https://dlilien.github.io/post/egrip/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dlilien.github.io/post/egrip/</guid>
      <description>I was supposed to go in Greenland in 2019, but that was canceled after there were issues with the force required to break the ice core. We then missed two seasons due to COVID, after which it was beginning to seem like I would never make it to Greenland.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heading to Little Dome C</title>
      <link>https://dlilien.github.io/post/be-oi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2019 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dlilien.github.io/post/be-oi/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m really excited to get to be a part of the final surveys for selecting the site of the Beyond Epica Oldest Ice core.
The Project Beyond Epica is looking to drill an ice core containing a continuous 1.5 million year climate record, 700,000 years longer than exists presently.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I moved to Denmark</title>
      <link>https://dlilien.github.io/post/move_to_denmark/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2019 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dlilien.github.io/post/move_to_denmark/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve started a postdoc in Denmark, at the Center for Ice and Climate (now called Physics of Ice, Climate and Earth). I am really excited to be here, both for the opportunity to work in a new environment and because there is so much expertise in glaciology and ice-core science.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2019 South Pole field season</title>
      <link>https://dlilien.github.io/post/sp_s3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 11:33:40 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dlilien.github.io/post/sp_s3/</guid>
      <description>In December, I headed to the South Pole for a third field season, wrapping our survey of regional ice flow. Like last year, this was a very quick season with only about two weeks at the Pole. As in previous years, the field season was timed to span the solstice so as to get the warmest weather at the South Pole (~-10 F this year).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Radar processing</title>
      <link>https://dlilien.github.io/post/impdar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2018 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dlilien.github.io/post/impdar/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing some work to bring the St. Olaf deep radar processor (StODeep) up into this decade. I&amp;rsquo;ve had some time twiddling my thumbs while running ice-flow models, and I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing the work of migrating StODeep as I wait for the model runs. I&amp;rsquo;m not a fan of Matlab, so I&amp;rsquo;ve migrated things to Python.
A bit of background The St. Olaf Deep radar processor has a long history that I don&amp;rsquo;t fully know.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 South Pole Field Season</title>
      <link>https://dlilien.github.io/post/sp_s2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dlilien.github.io/post/sp_s2/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m freshly back from another field season in Antarctica. This was a quick one, with only about two weeks down at the South Pole, though with transit I was gone for just over a month. We were continuing GPS and radar surveys, logging boreholes, and checking on instruments that had overwintered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python Brownbag</title>
      <link>https://dlilien.github.io/post/python_demo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dlilien.github.io/post/python_demo/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m giving a short seminar on python for matlab users this Friday. I plan to give a short presentation on why grad students in Earth and Space Sciences might want to switch from Matlab, followed by prepared demos where people can follow along.
I&amp;rsquo;ll also introduce git, since I think it is probably more important for productivity than the matlab/python choice. Hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ll have a few open-source converts by the end of the week!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Workshop on social media for science communication</title>
      <link>https://dlilien.github.io/post/scicomm_twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dlilien.github.io/post/scicomm_twitter/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve hesitated to commit to attending a full quarter of science communication classes, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to take advantage of the half or 1-day workshops that the UW College of the Environment has been offering. This workshop was on using social media to communicate science, which means twitter just got a bunch of new accounts from UW scientists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2017 SPICEcore Meeting</title>
      <link>https://dlilien.github.io/post/spicecore/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dlilien.github.io/post/spicecore/</guid>
      <description>I attended the annual meeting of the scientists who work on the South Pole Ice Core (SPICEcore) last week, which was a great opportunity to learn about all the work that people are doing using the core. This meeting was held at the University of Washington, September 19-20, 2017, and had scientists from throughout the US in attendance.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
